How many times have you used the word "awesome" today?
كم مرة استخدمت كلمة (رائع) اليوم؟
Once? Twice? Seventeen times?
مرة؟ مرتين؟ سبع عشرة مرة؟
Do you remember what you were describing
هل تتذكر ما كنت تصفه
when you used the word?
عندما استخدمت تلك الكلمة؟
No, I didn't think so, because it's come down to this, people:
لا أعتقد ذلك والسبب هو، فلنواجه الأمر يا قوم:
You're using the word incorrectly,
أنكم تستخدمون الكلمة بشكل غير صحيح،
and tonight I hope to show you
والليلة أتمنى أن أريكم
how to put the "awe" back in "awesome."
كيف نعيد ال"واو" لكلمة "روعة".
Recently, I was dining at an outdoor cafe,
مؤخرا كنت أتناول عشائي في أحد المطاعم
and the server came up to our table,
فجاءت إحدى النادلات إلى طاولتنا،
and asked us if we had dined there before,
وسألتنا إن سبق وتناولنا عشاءنا هنا،
and I said, "Yes, yes, we have."
فقلت: “لها نعم لقد فعلنا،"
And she said, "Awesome."
فقالت " رائع".
And I thought, "Really?
فتساءلت: "حقا؟"
Awesome or just merely good
هل الأمر بالفعل رائع، أم بالكاد جيد
that we decided to visit your restaurant again?"
أننا قررنا زيارة مطعمكم مرة أخرى؟
The other day, one of my coworkers asked me
ذات يوم، سألني أحد زملائي بالعمل
if I could save that file as a PDF,
إن كان بإمكاني حفظ ملف على صيغة: PDF،
and I said, "Well, of course," and he said, "Awesome."
فأجبته: "حسنا، بالطبع، "فقال، "رائع".
Seriously, can saving anything as a PDF
هل يعتبر حفظ أي شيء على صيغة PDF
be awesome?
شيئا رائعا؟
Sadly, the frequent overuse of the word "awesome"
مع الأسف، فقد أخذ الاستعمال المفرط لكلمة “رائع"
has now replaced words like "great" and "thank you."
مكان كلمات مثل "عظيم" و"شكرا".
So Webster's dictionary defines the word "awesome"
وقد تم تعريف كلمة "رائع" بقاموس ويبستر
as fear mingled with admiration or reverence,
على أنه خوف مختلط بالإعجاب والتبجيل،
a feeling produced by something majestic.
شعور متولد عن شيء ذي هيبة.
Now, with that in mind,
الآن، وقد أصبح هذا واضحا،
was your Quiznos sandwich awesome?
هل كانت شطيرة الكوزينوس رائعة؟
How about that parking space? Was that awesome?
ماذا عن مكان ركن السيارة؟ هل كان رائعا؟
Or that game the other day? Was that awesome?
أو مباراة ذلك اليوم؟ هل كانت رائعة؟
The answer is no, no and no.
الإجابة هي لا ولا ولا.
A sandwich can be delicious,
قد تكون الشطيرة شهية،
that parking space can be nearby,
قد يكون مكان ركن السيارة قريبا،
and that game can be a blowout,
وقد تكون تلك المباراة ملتهبة،
but not everything can be awesome.
لكن لا يمكن لكل شيء أن يكون رائعا.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So when you use the word "awesome"
لذلك حين تستعمل كلمة "رائع"
to describe the most mundane of things,
لتصف معظم الأشياء العادية،
you're taking away the very power of the word.
فإنك تسلب من الكلمة قوتها الحقيقية.
This author says, "Snowy days
يقول هذا الكاتب، "أن يهطل الثلج
or finding money in your pants is awesome."
أو أن تجد نقودا في سروالك، كلاهما رائع."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Um, no, it is not,
حسنا، لا، ليس الأمر كذلك.
and we need to raise the bar for this poor schmuck. (Laughter)
وعلينا أن نرفع المستوى لهذا الأحمق المسكين. (ضحك)
So in other words, if you have everything, you value nothing.
بمعنى آخر، إن كنت تملك كل شيء، فإنك لن تقدر أي شيء.
It's a lot like drinking from a firehose
الأمر أشبه ما يكون بالشرب من خرطوم الإطفاء
like this jackass right here.
مثل هذا الأبله هنا.
There's no dynamic, there's no highs or lows,
لن تكون هناك حركة، لا ارتفاع ولا انخفاض،
if everything is awesome.
إن كان كل شيء رائعا.
Ladies and gentlemen, here are 10 things
سيداتي وساداتي، إليكم 10 أشياء
that are truly awesome.
رائعة بكل ما في الكلمة من معنى.
Imagine, if you will, having to schlep
تخيل إن كان عليك أن تحمل
everything on your back.
كل شيء على ظهرك
Wouldn't this be easier for me
ألن يكون من السهل علي
if I could roll this home?
أن أدحرج هذا حتى أصل إلى البيت؟
Yes, so I think I'll invent the wheel.
نعم، لذا فكرت، أن أخترع العجلة.
The wheel, ladies and gentlemen.
العجلة، أيها السيدات والسادة.
Is the wheel awesome? Say it with me.
هل العجلة رائعة؟ قولوا معي.
Yes, the wheel is awesome!
أجل، العجلة رائعة!
The Great Pyramids were the tallest
كانت الأهرام الكبرى أطول
man-made structure in the world
البنايات التي صنعتها يد الإنسان في العالم
for 4,000 years.
ل 4000 سنة.
Pharaoh had his slaves move millions of blocks
كان عبيد فرعون يحركون ملايينا من قطع الطوب
just to this site to erect a big freaking headstone.
إلى هذا الموقع فقط لينصب قبره الغريب؟
Were the Great Pyramids awesome?
هل كانت الأهرام رائعة؟
Yes, the pyramids were awesome.
أجل، كانت الأهرام رائعة.
The Grand Canyon. Come on.
الأخدود العظيم، بربكم.
It's almost 80 million years old.
يبلغ عمره 80 مليون سنة.
Is the Grand Canyon awesome?
هل يعتبر الأخدود العظيم رائعا؟
Yes, the Grand Canyon is.
نعم الأخدود العظيم كذلك.
Louis Daguerre invented photography in 1829,
اخترع لويس داغير التصوير سنة 1829،
and earlier today,
وفي وقت سابق اليوم،
when you whipped out your smartphone
عندما كنت تمسح على هاتفك الذكي،
and you took a shot of your awesome sandwich,
وأخذت صورة لشطيرتك الرائعة،
and you know who you are —
وأنت تعلم عمن أتحدث--
(Laughter) —
(ضحك)--
wasn't that easier than exposing the image
ألم يكن هذا أكثر بساطة من عرض صورة
to copper plates coated with iodized silver?
لصحون فضية معالجة باليود؟
I mean, come on. Is photography awesome?
أعني، بحقكم، أليس التصوير رائعا؟
Yes, photography is awesome.
نعم، التصوير رائع.
D-Day, June 6, 1944,
اليوم الحاسم، السادس من يونيو، 1944،
the Allied invasion of Normandy,
غزو الحلفاء لنورماندي
the largest amphibious invasion in world history.
أجبر غزو بري بحري في تاريخ العالم.
Was D-Day awesome? Yes, it was awesome.
هل كان اليوم الحاسم رائعا؟ نعم كان كذلك.
Did you eat food today? Did you eat?
هل أكلت طعاما اليوم؟ هل أكلت؟
Then you can thank the honeybee, that's the one,
إذن فيمكنك أن تشكر النحلة، هذه هي،
because if crops aren't pollinated, we can't grow food,
لأنه إن لم تلقح المحاصيل، فلن نستطيع إنبات الطعام،
and then we're all going to die.
وسنموت حينها جميعا.
It's just like that.
بكل بساطة.
But it's not like a flower can just get up
فالأمر لا يتم بأن تقوم زهرة
and have sex with another flower,
لتقيم علاقة مع زهرة أخرى،
although that would be awesome.
بالرغم من أن هذا سيكون رائعا.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Bees are awesome. Are you kidding me?
النحل رائع. هل تمزحون؟
Landing on the moon! Come on!
الهبوط على القمر! بربكم!
Apollo 11. Are you kidding me?
أبولو 11. هل تمزحون؟
Sixty-six years after the Wright Brothers
66 سنة بعد إقلاع الأخوين رايت
took off from Kitty Hawk, North Carolina,
من كيتي هاوك، كارولينا الشمالية،
Neil Armstrong was 240,000 miles away.
كان نيل أرمسترونغ على بعد 240000 ميلا.
That's like from here to the moon.
المسافة من هنا إلى القمر.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
That's one small step for a man,
كانت تلك خطوة صغيرة من رجل،
one giant leap for awesome!
وطفرة كبيرة بالنسبة للروعة!
You're damn right, it was.
أنتم محقون فعلا. فالأمر فعلا كان كذلك.
Woodstock, 1969: Rolling Stone Magazine said
وودستوك، 1969: قالت مجلة رولينغ ستون
this changed the history of rock and roll.
أن هذا قد غير تاريخ موسيقى الروك أند رول.
Tickets were only 24 dollars back then.
كان ثمن التذاكر حينها 24 دولارا فقط.
You can't even buy a freaking t-shirt for that now.
لا يمكنك أن تشتري قميصا غبيا بهذا الثمن الآن.
Jimi Hendrix's version of "The Star-Spangled Banner"
نسخة جيمي هاندريكس لأغنية "ذ ستار سبانجلد بانر"
was the most iconic.
كانت الأكثر تميزا.
Was Woodstock awesome? Yes, it was awesome.
هل كان وودستوك رائعا؟ أجل لقد كان رائعا.
Sharks! They're at the top of the food chain.
أسماك القرش! هم في أعلى القائمة للسلسلة الغذائية.
Sharks have multiple rows of teeth
لأسماك القرش العديد من صفوف الأسنان
that grow in their jaw
التي تنمو داخل فكها
and they move forward like a conveyor belt.
والتي تتحرك قدما كالحزام الناقل.
Some sharks can lose 30,000 teeth in their lifetime.
تفقد بعض أسماك القرش 30000 سنا في حياتها.
Does awesome inspire fear?
هل توحي الروعة بالخوف؟
Oh, hell yeah, sharks are awesome!
أوه؛ أجل؛ فأسماك القرش رائعة!
The Internet was born in 1982
ولدت الانترنت سنة 1982
and it instantly took over global communication,
وبسرعة استولت على التواصل العالمي،
and later tonight, when all these PowerPoints
ولاحقا الليلة، حين سيتم رفع كل هذه العروض
are uplifted to the Internet
على الانترنت
so that a guy in Siberia can get drunk
حتى يثمل رجل ما في سيبيريا
and watch this crap,
ويشاهد هذا الهراء.
the Internet is awesome.
الانترنت رائعة.
And finally, finally some of you can't wait
وفي النهاية، أخيرا يتحرق بعضكم
to come up and tell me how awesome my PowerPoint was.
للصعود هنا ليقولوا لي كم كان عرض الباوربوينت الخاص بي رائعا.
I will save you the time.
سأوفر عليكم الوقت.
It was not awesome, but it was true,
لم يكن رائعا، بل كان حقيقيا،
and I hope it was entertaining,
وأتمنى أنه كان ترفيهيا،
and out of all the audiences I've ever had,
ومن بين الحضور الذين قابلتهم من قبل،
y'all are the most recent. Thank you and good night.
فأنتم الأحدث. شكرا لكم وطابت ليلتكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)